Guide to the Robert Maynard Hutchins Papers 1884-2000
University of Chicago Library
- Series XII: Audiovisual
  - 7-inch reel - Side 1: "Higher Education," library conversation with Stringfellow Barr and Donald McDonald, March 13, 1972. Side 2: Reads three-minute statement as an introduction to Jubal Parten's account of House Un-American Activities Committee hearing, March 6, 1972. Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track. (Box 449)
  - 7-inch reel - Side 1: Closing Remarks (approximately 5 minutes), Center Convocation, International Ballroom, Beverly Hilton Hotel, Los Angeles, January 27, 1973. Side 2: Robert M. Hutchins reading appeal for support of public broadcasting (approximately 3 minutes), March 30, 1973. Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: good. (Box 449)
  - 7-inch reel - "The Great American Baby-Sitting Machine: Our School System," Garry Wills and Robert M. Hutchins, May 3, 1972. (See catalog). Dub. Speed: 7 1/2 ips, full track, Time: 25:59. (Box 449)
  - 7-inch reel - Sides 1 & 2: Robert M. Hutchins and Joseph Schwab, "The Public Interest in Education: Toward a Policy for the United States," March 19, 1973 (a.m.). Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: good. (Box 449)
  - 7-inch reel - Sides 1 & 2: Robert M. Hutchins and Joseph Schwab, "The Public Interest in Education," March 19, 1973 (p.m.). Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: good. (Box 449)
  - 7-inch reel - Sides 1 & 2: "The Public Interest in Education," conference continued, March 20, 1973. Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: good (Box 450)
  - 7-inch reel - Side 1: "The Public Interest in Education," conference continued, March 20, 1973 (p.m.). Side 2: "What Can We Do About Public Education?" Robert M. Hutchins remarks at Houston meeting (approximately 7 minutes), introduced by Major Jubal Parton (rest of material apparently prerecorded and unrelated), March 3, 1973. Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: good. (Box 450)
  - 7-inch reel - Sides 1 & 2: Robert M. Hutchins interviewed by George Dell, Center for Study of Democratic Institutions, May 29, 1973, May 30, 1973, and June 1, 1973. Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: side 1 is poor to good with some distortion, side 2 is good. (Box 450)
  - 7-inch reel - Side 1: Robert M. Hutchins, John Cogley, Joseph Schwab, Thomas Cronin, Harvey Wheeler, library conversation on Watergate, Center for Study of Democratic Institutions, July 3, 1973. Side 2: "Pacem in Terris," III Convocation, Robert M. Hutchins opening and closing statements, October 8, 1973 (evening) and October 10, 1973 (p.m.). Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: good. (Box 450)
  - 7-inch reel - Side 1: Robert M. Hutchins introduction of Milton Mayer at dinner party, Center for Study of Democratic Institutions, December 11, 1973. Conference on Constitutional Principles, excerpts, December 12, 1973. Side 2: Robert M. Hutchins opening remarks, Conference on "Social and Political Change-The Role of Women," Center for Study of Democratic Institutions, March 7, 1974. Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: good. (Box 450)
  - 7-inch reel - Sides 1 & 2: "Constitutional Principles," Robert M. Hutchins discussion with Harvey Wheeler, Center for Study of Democratic Institutions, December 14, 1973. Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: good. (Box 450)
  - 7-inch reel - Side 1 and part of Side 2: "American Educational System" talk to the University of Chicago Club of Santa Barbara, Robert M. Hutchins with Joseph Schwab, December 15, 1973. Side 2: "State of the Democratic Process" Convocation, International Ballroom, Beverly Hilton Hotel, Los Angeles, with Daniel Seniel Ostrow, June 1, 1974 (a.m.), 5 minutes. Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: good. (Box 450)
  - 7-inch reel - Sides 1 & 2: "The Public Interest in Education: The Constitutional Aspects," Center for Study of Democratic Institutions, September 6, 1974 and November 30, 1974. Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: good. (Box 450)
  - 7-inch reel - Side 1: Robert M. Hutchins talks with Clifton Fadiman in Center for Study of Democratic Institutions library ("What is the driving force of your life?"), March 20, 1975. Side 2: Conversation with Eric Severeid, CBS-TV, edited program, recorded from channel 2 TV, August 31, 1975. Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: good. (Box 450)
  - 7-inch reel - Side 1: "The Environment and the Right to Housing." preliminary meeting in preparation for November 7-8, 1975, conference on "Where Shall We Live?" led by Robert M. Hutchins, September 26, 1975. Side 2: After-dinner speeches, Conference on "Where Shall We Live?" Robert M. Hutchins, John Simon, and Thomas Pettigrew, November 7, 1975 (evening). Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: good. (Box 450)
  - 7-inch reel - Sides 1 & 2: "Is Democracy Possible?" Hutchins' paper read and commented on by Otis Graham and Robert Kelly of the University of California Santa Barbara, recorded by SBCC for Adult Education Series, October 13, 1975. Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: good. (Box 450)
  - 7-inch reel - Sides 1 & 2: "Where Shall We Live?" conference Opening Session, with Harold Fleming of Potomac Institute, November 7, 1975 (a.m.). Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: good, but with slight distortion at the beginning. (Box 450)
  - 7-inch reel - Sides 1 & 2: "Where Shall We Live?" conference, continued, November 7, 1975 (p.m.). Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: good. (Box 450)
  - 7-inch reel - Sides 1 & 2: "Where Shall We Live?" conference, continued, November 8, 1975 (a.m.). Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: good. (Box 450)
  - 7-inch reel - Side 1: "Pacem in Terris" IV, opening session, (very short), December 2, 1975 (a.m.). Side 2: Robert M. Hutchins introduces Harold C. Fleming at after dinner discussion on "Where Shall We Live?" May 7, 1976. Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: good. (Box 451)
  - 7-inch reel - Sides 1 & 2: "Where Shall We Live? II," Center for Study of Democratic Institutions, May 7, 1976. Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: good. (Box 451)
  - 7-inch reel - Sides 1 & 2: "Democracy and Socialism," Robert M. Hutchins, Mortimer Adler, and William Gorman, panel discussion for Center Support Group, May 22, 1976. Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: poor. (Box 451)
  - 7-inch reel - "Democracy and Socialism: The Declaration of Independence and the Communist Manifesto," Robert M. Hutchins, Mortimer Adler, and William Gorman, May 22, 1976. Speed: 7 1/2 ips, full track, Quality: good. (Box 451)
  - 7-inch reel - "Democracy and Socialism: The Declaration of Independence and the Communist Manifesto," Robert M. Hutchins, Mortimer Adler, and William Gorman, May 22, 1976. Speed: 7 1/2 ips, full track, Quality: good. (Box 451)
  - 7-inch reel - Sides 1 & 2: Robert M. Hutchins interviewed by George Dell, Center for Study of Democratic Institutions, May 24-25, 1976. Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: good. (Box 451)
  - 7-inch reel - Side 1: "Higher Education Then and Now," Center for Study of Democratic Institutions, September 1, 1976. Side 2: Remarks at Seneil Ostrow's Birthday Party, September 10, 1976. Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: good. (Box 451)
  - 7-inch reel - Side 1: "Planning the Program for 1976–77," Center for Study of Democratic Institutions, September 17, 1976. Side 2: "To a World Society," with Otis Graham at Lobero Theater, Santa Barbara, October 11, 1976. Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: poor to good. (Box 451)
  - 7-inch reel - Side 1: Robert M. Hutchins, interviewed by George Dell, January 13, 1977. Side 2: "What Kind of President Do We Need?" Robert M. Hutchins and John Cogley, April 30, 1974. Dub. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: good. (Box 451)
  - 7-inch reel - "The Life and Thought of Robert M. Hutchins," Series III: "Educational Philosophy," Mortimer Adler, William Gorman, and Harry S. Ashmore, 1 Side only, November 21, 1977. Speed: 7 1/2 ips, full track, Quality: good. [1/4] (Box 451)
  - 7-inch reel - "The Life and Thought of Robert M. Hutchins," Series III: "Educational Philosophy," Mortimer Adler, William Gorman, and Harry S. Ashmore, 1 Side only, November 21, 1977. Speed: 7 1/2 ips, full track, Quality: good. [2/4] (Box 451)
  - 7-inch reel - "The Life and Thought of Robert M. Hutchins," Series III: "Educational Philosophy," Mortimer Adler, William Gorman, and Harry S. Ashmore, 1 Side only, November 21, 1977. Speed: 7 1/2 ips, full track, Quality: good. [3/4] (Box 451)
  - 7-inch reel - "The Life and Thought of Robert M. Hutchins," Series III: "Educational Philosophy," Mortimer Adler, William Gorman, and Harry S. Ashmore, 1 Side only, November 21, 1977. Speed: 7 1/2 ips, full track, Quality: good. [4/4] (Box 451)
  - 7-inch reel - "The Life and Thought of Robert M. Hutchins," Series IV, "World Order Under Law," Norman Cousins, Elisabeth Mann Borgese, and Otis Graham, November 28, 1977 (evening). Speed: 7 1/2 ips, full track, Quality: good. [1/4] (Box 451)
  - 7-inch reel - "The Life and Thought of Robert M. Hutchins," Series IV, "World Order Under Law," Norman Cousins, Elisabeth Mann Borgese, and Otis Graham, November 28, 1977 (evening). Speed: 7 1/2 ips, full track, Quality: good. [2/4] (Box 452)
  - 7-inch reel - "The Life and Thought of Robert M. Hutchins," Series IV, "World Order Under Law," Norman Cousins, Elisabeth Mann Borgese, and Otis Graham, November 28, 1977 (evening). Speed: 7 1/2 ips, full track, Quality: good. [3/4] (Box 452)
  - 7-inch reel - "The Life and Thought of Robert M. Hutchins," Series IV, "World Order Under Law," Norman Cousins, Elisabeth Mann Borgese, and Otis Graham, November 28, 1977 (evening). Speed: 7 1/2 ips, full track, Quality: good. [4/4] (Box 452)
  - 7-inch reel - Side 1: Robert Hutchins on American Public Education and the Law, particularly the Tinker Case in Des Moines, Iowa, undated. Side 2: Robert M. Hutchins' Introduction of Berkeley Professor of Psychology, undated. [These two sessions were not as originally labeled on the tape Box]. Speed: 3 3/4 ips, one-half track, Quality: good. (Box 452)
- Series XIII: Books
  This series contains annotated books from Hutchins' personal library and loose-leaf notes found enclosed.
  - Aeschylus, The House of Atreus, trans. E. D. A. Morshead, 1928 (Box 453)
  - Ames, James Barr, Lectures on Legal History, 1920 (Box 453)
  - Anselm, Proslogium, Monologium, An Appendix in Behalf of the Fool by Gaunilon, and Cur Deus Homo, trans. Sidney Norton Deane, 1939 (Box 453)
  - Aurelius Antonius, Marcus, The Thoughts of Marcus Aurelius Antonius, trans. John Jackson, 1928 (Box 453)
  - Beers, Henry A., The Ways of Yale in the Consulship of Plancus, 1910 (Box 453)
  - Beers, Henry A., The Ways of Yale in the Consulship of Plancus, 1923 (Box 453)
  - Bentham, Jeremy, Principles of Morals and Legislation, 1907 (Box 453)
  - Boswell, James, The Life of Samuel Johnson, undated (Box 453)
  - Brown, Charles Reynolds, Yale Talks, 1920 (Box 454)
  - Burke, Edmund, Reflections on the French Revolution and Other Essays, 1919 (Box 454)
  - Carlyle, Thomas and Ralph Waldo Emerson, Correspondence, 1886 (Box 454)
  - Cicero, Nine Orations, introduction and notes by Albert Harkness, 1906 (Box 454)
  - Conrad, Joseph, Under Western Eyes, 1951 (Box 454)
  - Descartes, Rene, A Discourse on Method, trans. Veitch, John, 1927 (Box 454)
  - Euclid, Elements, ed. Isaac Todhunter, 1939 (Box 454)
  - Fisher, Herbert, Napoleon, 1913 (Box 454)
  - Notes on Euclid, Elements, undated (Box 454, Folder 1)
  - Hamilton, Alexander, James Madison, and John Jay, The Federalist, 1919, Hinton, Edward W., Cases on Code Pleading, 1922 Kant, Immanuel, Perpetual Peace, 1932 Kant, Immanuel, Fundamental Principles of the Metaphysic of Ethics [Morals], trans. Thomas Kingsmill Abbott, 1932 Kant, Immanuel, Prolegomena to Any Future Metaphysics, ed. Paul Carus, 1929 Kierkegaard, Soren, Philosophical Fragments, trans. David F. Swenson, 1946 (Box 455, Folder 1)
  - Locke, John, Two Treatises of Civil Government, 1924 (Box 455, Folder 2)
  - Notes on Hamilton, Alexander, James Madison, and John Jay, The Federalist, undated (Box 455, Folder 3)
  - Notes on Kant, Immanuel, Fundamental Principles of the Metaphysic of Ethics [Morals], undated (Box 455, Folder 4)
  - Lorenzen, Ernest, Cases on the Conflict of Laws, 1924 (Box 456)
  - Luther, Martin, Three Treatises, 1947 (Box 456)
  - Machiavelli, Niccolo, The Prince, 1928 (Box 456)
  - Marx, Karl, Capital, trans. Samuel Moore and Edward Aveling, 1936 (Box 456)
  - Notes on Machiavelli, Niccolo, The Prince, undated (Box 456, Folder 1)
  - Notes on Marx, Karl, Capital, undated (Box 456, Folder 2)
  - Mason, Alpheus Thomas, The Supreme Court from Taft to Warren, 1958 (Box 457)
  - Melville, Herman, Moby Dick, 1926 (Box 457)
  - Milton, John, Paradise Lost, undated (Box 457)
  - Montaigne, Michel de, Essayes, Vol. 3, trans. John Florio, 1928 (Box 457)
  - Muir, Ramsay, National Self-Government, 1918 (Box 457)
  - Oliphant, Herman, Cases on Trade Regulation, 1923 (Box 457)
  - Notes on Montaigne, Michel de, Essayes, Vol. 3, undated (Box 457, Folder 1)
  - Ortega y Gasset, José, Mission of the University, trans. Howard Lee Nostrand, 1944 (Box 458)
  - Plato, Apology, Crito, Republic I-II, 1947 (Box 458)
  - Pound, Ezra, Culture, 1938 (Box 458)
  - Rousseau, Jean Jacques, Emile, or Education, trans. Barbara Foxley, 1933 (Box 458)
  - Ruskin, John, Unto This Last and Other Essays, 1913 (Box 458)
  - Santayana, George, Character and Opinion in the United States, 1920 (Box 458)
  - Swinburne, Algernon Charles, Poems, 1884, Taussig, F. W., Principles of Economics, Vol. I, 1915 (Box 458, Folder 1)
  - Taussig, F. W., Principles of Economics, Vol. II, 1916 (Box 459)
  - Wood, John Seymour, Yale Yarns, 1897 (Box 459)
  - Woodward, Frederic Campbell, Cases on the Law of Sales of Goods, 1913 (Box 459)
  - Yale College, A History of the Class of 1921, ed. Lift, Willard D., 1921 (Box 459)
  - Yale College, Class of 1921, The Quarter-Century Chronicle, ed. Philip O'Brien, 1946 (Box 459)
  - Yale University, Freshman Blue Book, 1916 (Box 459)
- Series XIV: Oversize
  This series contains oversize materials including honors and awards, photographs, posters and broadsides, an issue of the Saturday Evening Post, and academic regalia.
  - Encyclopædia Britannica certificate, framed, 1974 (Box 460, Folder 1)
  - Saturday Evening Post, December 11, 1937 (Box 460, Folder 2)
  - Congratulatory broadside from Harvard upon Hutchins' inauguration as President of the University of Chicago, 1929 (Box 460, Folder 3)
  - Portfolio presentation, The Genealogical Foundation, 1932 (Box 460, Folder 4)
  - Tulane University, Doctor of Laws diploma, 1938 (Box 460, Folder 5)
  - Goethe Award commemorative certificate, bound, 1949 (Box 460, Folder 6)
  - Business and Professional Associates of the American Jewish Congress certificate, bound, 1956 (Box 460, Folder 7)
  - Oberlin College diploma, 1915 (Box 460, Folder 8)
  - Yale University Bachelor of Arts diploma, 1921 (Box 460, Folder 9)
  - Yale University Master of Arts diploma, 1922 (Box 460, Folder 10)
  - Yale University Bachelor of Laws diploma, 1925 (Box 460, Folder 11)
  - Johann Wolfgang Goethe University of Frankfurt, Honorary Doctorate certificate, 1948 (Box 460, Folder 12)
  - Georgetown University, Honorary Doctorate diploma, 1964 (Box 460, Folder 13)
  - Rollins College, Honorary Doctorate diploma, 1968 (Box 460, Folder 14)
  - Photographs, 1932, 1969, and undated (Box 460, Folder 15)
  - Poster, Oriel College, Oxford University, 1919 (Box 460, Folder 16)
  - Légion d'Honneur certificate, 1937 (Box 460, Folder 17)
  - Honorary Doctorate diploma, 1949 (Box 460, Folder 18)
  - Hebrew Union College, Honorary Doctorate diploma, 1965 (Box 460, Folder 19)
  - Cartoon – “Relative Importance of Two Announcements,” Chicago Tribune, 1930. Original drawing inscribed by artist John T. McCutcheon to Hutchins. (Box 460, Folder 20)
  - Liberal Arts Foundation seal embosser (Box 461)
  - 7 Academic hoods, 1940s-1960s (Box 462)
- Series XV: Restricted
  This series contains files to which access is restricted. Subseries 1 contains financial and personnel materials, restricted for 50 years from date of record creation. Subseries 1 as a whole will be fully open in 2027. Subseries 2 contains evaluative student material, which is restricted for 80 years from date of record creation. Subseries 2 as a whole will be fully open in 2055.
  - Subseries 1: Financial and Personnel Information
    - University of Chicago - Board of Trustees - Financial reports, 1971-1975 (Box 463, Folder 1)
    - University of Chicago - Statement of investments, 1974 (Box 463, Folder 2)
    - University of Chicago - Statement of investments, 1975 (Box 463, Folder 3)
    - University of Chicago - Committee on Organization and Nominating Committee, 1970-1977 (Box 463, Folder 4)
    - University of Chicago - Committee on Organization and Nominating Committee, 1970-1973 (Box 463, Folder 5)
    - University of Chicago - Committee on Organization and Nominating Committee, 1970 (Box 463, Folder 6)
    - Fund for the Republic - Finances, 1974 (Box 463, Folder 7)
    - Fund for the Republic - Financial report, 1975 (Box 464, Folder 1)
    - Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions - Endowment campaign, 1966-1973 (Box 464, Folder 2)
    - Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions - Investment Committee - Meetings, 1967-1968 (Box 464, Folder 3)
    - Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions - Reorganization, 1969-1970 (Box 464, Folder 4)
    - Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions - Reorganization, 1969 (Box 464, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 2: Student Information
    - Evaluative material re student, 1940-1941 (Box 465, Folder 1)
    - Hadley, Arlene, 1945 (Box 465, Folder 2)
    - Sawyer, Elizabeth Ann, 1947 (Box 465, Folder 3)
    - Bush, Prescott, 1950 (Box 465, Folder 4)
    - "The Great Books Program," Franklin Parker, 1953 (Box 465, Folder 5)
    - Recommendations, 1962-1975 (Box 465, Folder 6)
    - Recommendations, 1965-1966 (Box 465, Folder 7)